Guide to the Carl Feiss papers, [ca.1928]-1991
Feiss, Carl papers, [ca.1928]-1991
- Series II. Professional Papers
  - Organizations
    - Urban Design Committee, AIA: correspondence; memoranda; "Listing of Publications Recently Received in the AIA Office of Urban Programs," April 1969; meeting minutes; "Resolution of the AIA Commission on the Environment," October 10, 1969; "Outline for proposed 1969 Research Program," January 28, 1969. (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - Urban Design Committee, AIA: correspondence; memoranda; brochure; Budget and Work Program status, September 1969; AIP Policy, April 1969. (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - Environmental Design Legislation for States, AIA: correspondence; "Environmental Design Legislation for States," June 21, 1969; "The Role of the State in Environmental Design Recommended Action to the AIA Urban Design Committee Derived from the Draft Report of March 14, 1969." (Box 13, Folder 12)
    - Environmental Design Legislation for States, AIA: correspondence; "Possible Legislative Proposals for National Urban Growth Policy," February 19, 1969; Letter: A Report on Environmental Issues from The Conservation Foundation, March 17, 1969 (Box 13, Folder 13)
    - Urban Design Committee, AIA: correspondence; meeting minutes; meeting agendas; memoranda; "Supercity: A Prototype for the U.S.A.," by Lloyd Ruocco, April 3-4, 1968, 1969 (Box 13, Folder 14)
    - New Towns Communities Program, AIA: correspondence; "New Communities Program for the AIA 1968-1969," October 18, 1968.; clippings from New York Times November 27, 1968 and U.S. News and World Report, October 21, 1968 (Box 13, Folder 15)
    - Urban Design Committee, AIA: correspondence, memoranda, meeting minutes; meeting agendas., 1968 (Box 13, Folder 16)
    - Committee on Urban Design, AIA: correspondence, "Listing of Publications Recently Received in the AIA Office of Urban Programs," August 1968; meeting minutes; meeting agendas; memoranda; "Suggestions for future AIA conventions.", 1967-1968 (Box 13, Folder 17)
    - Committee on Urban Design, AIA: correspondence, meeting minutes, meeting agendas; memoranda, project proposal for "Urban Design Assistance Teams.", 1967 (Box 13, Folder 18)
    - New Towns Communities Program, AIA: letter from A.F. Euston, Jr., Director, Urban Programs to Urban Design Committee re: "Advisory Commission on Intergovernmental Relations New Towns Prospectus," February 28, 1967. (Box 13, Folder 19)
    - Committee on Urban Design, AIA: correspondence, meeting minutes, meeting agendas; memoranda., 1967-1966 (Box 13, Folder 20)
    - Committee on Urban Design, AIA: correspondence; meeting minutes; "A New Weapon for the ?War on Community Ugliness,'" prepared by Committee on Aesthetics, AIA, November 4, 1965; The General Electric Forum, October-December 1965; request for funds by the Urban Design Committee, 1966; "Assignments made to Urban Design Committee Members, February 15, 1965;" poster for the AIA's first workshop in Urban Design, November 18-20, 1965., 1966-1965 (Box 13, Folder 21)
    - Urban Design Series, AIA: Urban Design Papers #1-9., 1964 (Box 13, Folder 22)
    - Urban Design Committee, AIA: correspondence, meeting minutes, meeting agendas, memoranda., 1964 (Box 13, Folder 23)
    - Committee on Historic Resources, AIA: correspondence, meeting minutes, meeting agendas, memoranda., 1973-1972 (Box 13, Folder 24)
    - Committee on Historic Resources, AIA: correspondence; Committee on Historic Resources/State Preservation Coordinator Council Newsletter, April 1971, July 1971; list of CHR 1971 members; roster of state preservation coordinators, June 1970; "The Architect as a Preservationist," 1971; Historic Resources Committee Bicentennial Survey., 1970-1971 (Box 13, Folder 25)
    - Committee on Historic Resources, AIA: correspondence; questionnaire; meeting minutes; meeting agendas; Committee on Historic Resources/State Preservation Coordinator Council Newsletter, August 1970; brochure from AIP on building preservation; "Services of the Architect/Engineer on Restoration Projects," by Orin M. Bullock, Jr., November 14, 1968; "Specialized Services of the Architectural Restoration Consultant," by Orin M. Bullock, Jr.; "Statement by the AIA regarding H.R. 14896, a Bill to Amend and Extend the Historic Properties Act of 1966, before the House Committee on Interior and Insular Affairs Subcommittee on National Parks and Recreation," January 29, 1970., 1970-1971 (Box 13, Folder 26)
    - Committee on Historic Buildings, AIA: correspondence; photograph; program for the First Annual Indiana Conference on Historic Preservation, Bloomington, Indiana, September 18-20, 1969. (Box 13, Folder 27)
    - Committee on Preservation of Historic Buildings: correspondence, 1964 (Box 13, Folder 28)
    - Committee on International Relations, AIA: list of 1972 members; notes; provisional program of the 11th World Congress of the International Union of Architects, Bulgaria, 1972; working draft of "World Heritage Trust Convention Concerning the Preservation and Protection of Natural Areas and Cultural Sites of Universal Value," March 28, 1972; "Activities of the International Union of Architects," by Daniel Schwartzman, March 30, 1972., 1971-1972 (Box 13, Folder 29)
    - Committee on International Relations, AIA: correspondence, meeting minutes, meeting agendas; memoranda., 1972 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Union Internationale des Architectes: AIA Journal, November 1970; list of "invited foreign architects for the UIA Town Planning Commission Meeting, Washington, D.C., September 21-25, 1970; list of 1969 committee on International Relations; preliminary program as of December 1968 for 10th World Congress of Architects to take place October 1969 in Buenos Aires., 1968-1970 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Union Internationale des Architectes: correspondence, meeting minutes, meeting agendas, memoranda, preliminary program as of May 1969 for 10th World Congress of Architects to take place October 1969 in Buenos Aires; program from 14th Meeting of the Schoolbuilding Commission of the UIA, Stresa, September 16-21, 1968., 1970 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Committee on International Relations, AIA: correspondence; meeting minutes; "The Architect on Stage," by G.E. Kassabaum, October 7-11, 1968; list of candidates for Honorary Fellow, AIA, 1969; budget estimate for UIA Town Planning Commission Meeting, Washington, D.C., 1970., 1967-1969 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Committee on International Relations, AIA: meeting agenda, memorandum, Worldwide P & I Planning, May/June-July/August 1967. (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Committee on International Relations, AIA: correspondence, meeting minutes, memoranda, "Report of the United Nations Interregional Seminar on Development Policies and Planning in Relation to Urbanization," Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, October 24-November 4, 1966; draft of "An Interim Report: An Assessment of the Possibilities for Joint Design Profession on an Inter-American Basis," by Richard Sharp, May 8, 1967. (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Committee on International Relations, AIA: Carnegie Review, October 1966; notes; correspondence, memoranda; application for honorary fellow candidate, AIA. (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Union Internationale des Architectes: International conferences: program for 8th World Congress of the International Union of Architects, Paris, 1965; list of participants of 1st General Assembly of International Council of Monuments and Sites, Versovie-Cracovie, June 20-27, 1965; program for 1st International Festival of Architectural Film, Paris, July 5-9, 1965; program for Study and Congress Tour of North American Architects, July 3-25, 1965; notes; papers. (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Union Internationale des Architectes: correspondence; meeting minutes; meeting agendas; reports; list of "candidates for honorary fellowships in 1965 held over for consideration from the listing of 1964;" "names of honorary fellows and the year of their election;" list of UIA working commissions; schedule of international meetings, 1965., 1964-1965 (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - United States-Mexico border: correspondence; regional maps; "El Chamizal," AIA Journal, September 1964; "A Proposal for a Border Planning Commission, July 20, 1964; "Border Planning Events Since 1964 Board Report ? Most of Remarks Are Directed to Activity in El Paso-Juarez Metropolitan Area," October 16, 1964., 1964-1965 (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - Committee on International Relations, AIA: meeting minutes; meeting agendas; memoranda; reports; brochure by Edwin W. Carroll on the Texas national border., 1965 (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - Committee on International Relations, AIA: meeting agendas; memoranda; meeting minutes; correspondence; list of delegates at the 27th World Congress of the International Federation for Housing and Planning, Jerusalem, 1964, 1963-1966 (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - Committee on Legislation, AIA: meeting minutes; "Proposal for a Commitment to an Effective Government Relations Program by the AIA," December 1969; California 1969 Legislative Program; correspondence; memoranda; meeting agendas. (Box 14, Folder 13)
    - Committee on Legislation, AIA: correspondence; meeting minutes; "Statement of the AIA on H.R. 15624 ?Housing and Urban Development Act of 1969' Before the House Banking and Currency Committee Subcommittee on Housing," March 15, 1968; "Leadership in Legislation," by Philip A. Hutchinson, Jr., January 1968; program for Joint A-E Legislative Affairs Conference, January 30-31, 1968; tentative agenda for "AIA's Legislative Goals in Housing" Conference., 1967-1968 (Box 14, Folder 14)
    - Urban Growth and New Community Act: "Statement by AIA Regarding H.R. 16647?The Urban Growth and New Community Act of 1970 before the House Banking and Currency Committee Ad Hoc Subcommittee on Urban Growth," July 9, 1970; Feiss' draft of that statement, June 3, 1970. (Box 14, Folder 15)
    - Urban Growth and New Community Act: correspondence re: legislative recommendations for the Urban Growth and New Community Act, including published hearings and a testimony draft., 1970 (Box 14, Folder 16)
    - Urban Growth and New Community Act: drafts of Act, "It's High Time for Americans to Disperse," Washington Post, February 8, 1970; correspondence, memorandum. (Box 14, Folder 17)
    - Environmental legislation: Published hearings of H.R. 12549, an amendment "to provide for the establishment of a Council on Environmental Quality, and for other purposes;" "Testimony of AIA Before the Housing Banking and Currency Committee Ad Hoc Subcommittee on Urban Growth," September 30, 1965; correspondence, AIA press release, "Architects Ask Congress to Help Start 110 New Town," September 30, 1969. (Box 14, Folder 18)
    - Corporation for Community Development Act, Pennsylvania, 1969: correspondence; City Chronicle, November 1969; notes; draft of act; slide presentation for AIA testimony before the Ad Hoc Subcommittee on Urban Growth, House Banking and Currency Committee. S.2368, A Bill to Establish a National Institute of Building Sciences: testimony before the U.S. Senate Committee on Banking and Currency Subcommittee on Housing and Urban Affairs, July 21, 1969; memorandum. H.R. 13217, Balanced Urbanization Policy and Planning Act, 1969: published hearings; correspondence;"Towards a National Policy on Balanced Communities," by Orville Freeman, article in Minnesota Law Review, May 1969; "Official Map;" "Planned Unit Development;" Mandatory Dedication of Park and School Sites; "By Year 200 U.S. Will Need 272 New Towns," by Hugh Morris, article in Boston Sunday Globe, August 3, 1969. (Box 14, Folder 19)
    - H.R. 13217, Balanced Urbanization Policy and Planning Act, 1969: correspondence; notes; "Testimony of Carl Feiss before the Ad Hoc Subcommittee of the House Banking and Currency Committee on Urban Growth;" "Statement by Rex Allen to members of the Subcommittee on Urban Growth; memoranda; press release from the Office of the White House Press Secretary re: population growth, July 18, 1969. (Box 14, Folder 20)
    - R/UDAT, AIA (Regional Urban Design Assistance Team, American Institute of Architects), Hawaii: correspondence; Oahu Development Conference Annual Report, 1973; "Alternative Urban growth Strategies Based on the Use of Rapid Transit Summary," September 1973; State Zoning Map of Island of Oahu, City and County of Honolulu, August 1971; "Urban Design Study of the Honolulu Waterfront," October 1968; preliminary outlines for planned development-housing proposal, 1973-1974., 1968-1975 (Box 14, Folder 21)
    - AIA, Hawaii chapter: Honolulu City Planning Commission Standards; zoning and development applications; "Rules of the Department of General Planning for Processing Amendments to the Existing General Plan, Detailed Land Use Maps, and Development Land of the City and County of Honolulu;" "Rules Relating to Administrative Procedure Zoning Board of Appeals;" "Shoreline Setback Rules and Regulations of the City and County of Honolulu," June 1971; brochure for R/UDAT, 1974; business cards; correspondence; advertisements for books; Hawaii Architect, March 1974 (Box 14, Folder 22)
    - AIA, Hawaii chapter: clippings; correspondence; invoices; R/UDAT schedule, April 3, 1974; memoranda. (Box 14, Folder 23)
    - New Communities Conference, Washington, D.C., November 3-6, 1971: "Development Incentives and Controls for New Communities?An Overview;" correspondence; expense voucher; poster for New Communities Conference; brochure for Vienna National Town Planning Competition, 1971 (Box 14, Folder 24)
    - AIA-CEC Public Affairs Conference, Washington, D.C.: February 17-18, 1970: correspondence; program; memoranda; handbook; folder; Annual Report of the Committee on Legislation to the Board of Directors, AIA, October 1, 1969., 1969-1970 (Box 14, Folder 25)
    - Israeli-American Symposium on Architecture and Urban Design, Tel Aviv, Israel, September 27-October 12, 1969: program, correspondence; registration sheet. (Box 14, Folder 26)
    - Open Space for People: Acquisition, Conservation, Creation and Design. Ed. Mildred F. Schmertz, AIA. Washington, D.C.: American Institute of Architects, 1970. (Box 14, Folder 27)
    - AIA Annual Convention, Chicago, Illinois, June 22-26, 1969: "Proposed Bylaw Changes and Business Matters;" correspondence; memorandum. (Box 14, Folder 28)
    - Transcript of Proceedings: The American Institute of Architects Design in Federal Programs Workshop, Washington, D.C., September 8, 1967, pgs. 1-196. (Box 14, Folder 29)
    - Transcript of Proceedings: The American Institute of Architects Design in Federal Programs Workshop, Washington, D.C., September 8, 1967, pgs. 197-372. (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - AIA Annual Convention, Washington, D.C., June 14-18, 1965: papers, program; invitations; card of confirmation/preregistration. (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - AIA Annual Convention, Washington, D.C., June 14-18, 1965: correspondence; "The Architecture of Civilization;" program for 1st Annual Purves Memorial Lecture, Friday June 18, 1965; directory of product exhibitors. Notice of International Conference of the International Federation for Housing and Planning, June 27-July 3, 1965. AIA Memo, February 12, 1965. F.W. Dodge Construction News, July 2, 1965 (coverage of the convention). (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - "?And we rebuild our cities, not dream of islands," an address to AIA Annual Convention, 1957 reprinted in AIA Journal, June 1957. (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Memorandum, letter of agreement, and contract for Feiss' editorship of The Architect and Regional Planning., 1973 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - "Florida: The Seeds of Crisis," by Red Flag Charrette, March 3-5, 1972. (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Red Flag Charrette. "Development Incentives and Controls for New Communities?An Overview," address to The American Institute of Architects New Communities Conference, Washington, D.C., November 3-6, 1971. "Establishment of a National Land Use Policy," address to Committee on Interior and Insular Affairs, Washington, D.C., June 22, 1971. "Regional Planning," address to Subcommittee on Urban Affairs, Washington, D.C., May 19, 1971. Professional Correspondence. Planners Notebook, May 1971., 1972 (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence re: AIA, Hawaii chapter's nomination of Thomas H. Creighton for AIA's 1972 Architecture Critics Medal, October-November 1971. (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence re: Richard C. Frank's and Carrell S. McNulty, Jr.'s elevation to fellowship, AIA., 1971 (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - CDC/INFO (Community Development Centers Info): announcement of its publication, correspondence., 1971 (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - Land Use Policy: "Land Use, Planning and Management Programs: A Statement by Max O. Urbahn, FAIA President-elect, AIA to Subcommittee on Housing and Urban Affairs Committee on Banking, Housing and Urban Affairs," Washington D.C., July 14, 1978; correspondence re: Urbahn's statement., 1971 (Box 15, Folder 11)
    - Memorandum from AIA Regional Development and Natural Resources Committee to AIA Task Force on a National Environmental Policy re: Policy Recommendations, May 1, 1971. (Box 15, Folder 12)
    - Special Bulletin No. 2 on Proposed Ethical Standards, December 1969. AIA Document J330: "The Standards of Professional Practice," May 1967., 1967-1969 (Box 15, Folder 13)
    - Urban Design and Development Conference: notes, "Proposed New Communities Program," draft prepared by Feiss, April 16, 1969. (Box 15, Folder 14)
    - Reynolds Awards Program: correspondence; memoranda; notes; announcement of Fifth Annual Reynolds Aluminum Prize for Architectural Students, 1965; announcement of Ninth Annual R.S. Reynolds Memorial Award, 1965., 1965-1966 (Box 15, Folder 15)
    - AIA Board's Annual Report., 1959 (Box 15, Folder 16)
    - Distinguished Service Award of the American Institute of Planners: correspondence, nominations., 1977 (Box 15, Folder 17)
    - The Florida Planner, January 1975, April-June 1976. Draft of "What Do We Do Next With Florida?" Gainesville, Florida, March 5, 1972., 1972-1976 (Box 15, Folder 18)
    - Urban Design Committee, AIP: correspondence and memoranda re: its productivity and movements to abolish it; also establishment of Urban Design Department., 1970-1971 (Box 15, Folder 19)
    - Incorporation of AIP: consent form; National Capital Area Membership Roster, July 1969. Professional correspondence, including correspondence re: establishment of Urban Design Department and correspondence re: Julius Levine's nomination for Vice-President, AIP. Program for "A National Urban Growth Policy for the Future," Washington, D.C., January 28-31, 1971., 1969-1971 (Box 15, Folder 20)
    - Committee on Urban Design: correspondence, memoranda., 1968-1969 (Box 15, Folder 21)
    - ASPO National Planning Conference (American Society of Planning Officials), Cincinnati, Ohio, April 20-24, 1969: program, correspondence. 5th Biennial Conference on Government Relations and Planning Policy: Planning for Social Change, Washington, D.C., January 23-26, 1969: program, correspondence. (Box 15, Folder 22)
    - American Institute of Planners Conference, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, October 12-15, 1968: paper, poster, correspondence, program. (Box 15, Folder 23)
    - New Communities Act of 1968: published proceedings; draft report by Task Force on New Communities, February 21, 1968; correspondence. (Box 15, Folder 24)
    - American Institute of Planners Conference, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, October 12-15, 1968: correspondence. (Box 15, Folder 25)
    - "Statement of the American Institute of Planners presented by Robert L. Williams, AIP Executive Director, regarding S.3029 and S.2690 before the Senate Subcommittee on Banking and Currency Subcommittee on Housing," March 15, 1968. (Box 15, Folder 26)
    - Reference on current federal planning research: letter from AIP; Recent Research in Planning: A Reference, Department of Housing and Urban Development, 1968. "Small Business: An American Institute of Planners Background Paper," April 1967., 1967-1968 (Box 15, Folder 27)
    - AIP Urban Design Committee: correspondence., 1968 (Box 15, Folder 28)
    - AIP Urban Design Committee: correspondence and memoranda re: AIP's Policy Statement on Urban Design., 1967 (Box 15, Folder 29)
    - Comprehensive Development Planning, Programming and Coordination Act of 1967: background statement, section by section analysis. Government Relations and Planning Policy Conference, Washington, D.C., 1967: papers, registration form, program., 1966-1967 (Box 15, Folder 30)
    - "Planning and the Federal Establishment:" Proceedings of AIP's 4th Biennial Government Relations and Planning Policy Conference, Washington, D.C., January 27-29, 1967. (Box 15, Folder 31)
    - AIP's 50th Annual Conference: The Next Fifty Years?1967/2017, Washington, D.C., October 1-6, 1967: program, correspondence, clippings. (Box 15, Folder 32)
    - AIP's 50th Annual Conference: The Next Fifty Years?1967-2017, Washington, D.C., October 1-6, 1967: program summary; papers: "Status of AIP's 50th Year Consultation," by William Ewald; "Concerning the Hypthecation of a Philosophy on which to Build the Future Environment of a Democracy," by William Ewald; "A ?Stand-In' Philosophy for Building the Future Environment of a Democracy," by William Ewald; "Supplementary Projections for 1965-2020," by William Ewald. (Box 15, Folder 33)
    - AIP's 50th Annual Conference: The Next Fifty Years?1967-2017, Washington, D.C., October 1-6, 1967: committee of correspondence; papers: "Excerpts from the Original 1967 Commemorative Program Proposal;" "The Function and Operation of the Committee of Correspondence," by William Ewald; "Bibliography of Studies of Future Technology, Change and Philosophies of Life," by William Ewald. (Box 15, Folder 34)
    - AIP's 50th Annual Conference: The Next Fifty Years?1967-2017, Washington, D.C., October 1-6, 1967: list of available conference papers; papers: "Technology and the Underdeveloped World," by Renato Severino; "Taking Stock: A Resume of Planning Accomplishments in the United States" by Carl Feiss; "Housing in the Year 2000," by Charles Abrhams; "The New Factor in American Society," by David Bazelon; "The Future Man," by Pierre Bertaux; "The Culture of Urban America," by John Burhard; AIP Commemorative Program Proposals. (Box 15, Folder 35)
    - AIP's 50th Annual Conference: The Next Fifty Years?1967-2017, Washington, D.C., October 1-6, 1967: papers: "The Problems and Promise of Leisure," by Sebastian de Grazia; "On Forward Looking," by Betrand de Jouvenel; "Natural Resources?Wise Use of the World's Inheritance," by Joseph Fisher; "The People with Their Hands," by John Turner; "The Conscience of a Profession," by Dennis O'Harrow; address by Postmaster General Lawrence O'Brien; "Harnessing the Profit Motive to Better Planning," by Perry Prentice; "Manpower Needs for Planning for the Next Fifty Years," by Jack Meltzer; "The Next Fifty Years," by William Stewart. Conference press releases: "A Moral Coalition: New Answer to Urban Problems," "Planning for the 21st Century," "Anatomy of a Planner." (Box 15, Folder 36)
    - AIP's 50th Annual Conference: The Next Fifty Years?1967-2017, Washington, D.C., October 1-6, 1967: readings: Kaiser Aluminum News, no.1-6. Paper: "The Possible City," by Kevin Lynch. (Box 15, Folder 37)
    - AIP's 50th Annual Conference: The Next Fifty Years?1967-2017, Washington, D.C., October 1-6, 1967: papers: "New Incentives and Controls," by Daniel Mandelker; "Manpower Needs for Planning for the Next Fifty Years," by Jack Meltzer; "The Necessity and Difficulty of Planning the Future Society," by Gunnar Myrdal; "The Young Rebels," by Carl Oglesby; "Life Where Science Flows," by John Platt. (Box 15, Folder 38)